Finding Aid for Medical School (University of Michigan) records, 1850-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Medical School (University of Michigan) records 1850-2010
University of Michigan. Medical School.
1.8 GB
6 oversize folders
10 oversize volumes
338 linear feet
87253 Bimu C 46 2
Dean's files, including minutes of executive committee; records of subordinate administrative officers; faculty records, including minutes of faculty and executive faculty meetings; and collected historical materials, 1850-1949.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor 647 ) was first received in 1938. The bulk of the material was received in two large accessions, one in 1948 and the other in 1982. The library initiated captures of the Medical School website in 2010.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The Medical School records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files including search, review, promotion, and tenure files which are restricted for thirty years from date of creation; client/patient records which are restricted for 100 years from date of creation; and student educational records which are restricted for seventy-five years from the date of creation. In addition, records of the Medical School added to the record group after January 1, 2001 are restricted for twenty years from date of accession in accordance with the university's policy on the records of Executive Officers, Deans, Directors and their support offices.
The University of Michigan Medical School record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 178, 210-212, 238, 284, 308-310
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 144-149, 238, 260-269, 284, 308-310, 315-317, 324-338
Client/Patient Records -- Boxes 284, 308-310
Executive Officers Records -- Boxes 260-323
Pre-existing Restrictions -- Boxes 178, 210-212, 238, 248-251, 200-209, 239-247, 258-259
While the University of Michigan's charters of 1817 and 1837 both called for the inclusion of medical education within the curriculum, no action was taken to carry out this mandate until 1848. On January 19 of that year the regents appropriated funds for the construction of a building to house a new Medical Department. In the fall of 1850, when the building was completed, the first courses in medicine were taught.
The two available faculty members offered a six month course of study. Most material was taught through lectures. Ward rounds were perfunctory and no laboratory courses were required. A strict set of prerequisites for admission to the program existed, but in practice any student was admitted and then given up to two years to complete the prerequisite education. Administration was extremely limited. The "Rules of Government of the Medical College," adopted in July 1850, required the medical faculty to annually elect one of their number "president." By 1853, the title "president" had been superseded by that of "dean."
Throughout the nineteenth century the school grew and matured. The period of study lengthened, the number and type of courses grew, the quality of the students improved, and the administration of the college became more sophisticated. The length of study was increased repeatedly. In 1877-1878, the regents required of any student wishing to receive a medical degree one full academic year of study. At the same time an optional three year program was established. In 1880-1881, the three-year program was made mandatory, and in 1890-1891, the mandatory program was lengthened to four years.
The expanded amount of training naturally involved an increasing number of courses. Courses changed not only in number, however, but also in character. While lectures remained an important part of medical education, they were supplemented by mandatory laboratory courses and extensive rounds. The first mandatory laboratory course, anatomy, was initiated in 1852-1853. It was followed by qualitative chemistry, urine analysis, and histological work (microscopic analysis). In 1856-1857, the school's perfunctory rounds were superseded by more satisfactory clinics. The construction of the first university hospital in 1869, substantially increased in size in 1876 and again in 1879, gave students the opportunity to observe a variety of injuries and diseases.
Admission standards also changed. In 1874, written examinations were required of all candidates. In 1875-1876, candidates claiming other educational work were required to submit credentials. In 1903 a high school diploma was made mandatory for admission, and in 1912 a de facto rule of three years earlier requiring all candidates to have completed two years of college was stated explicitly. The first minimum grade point average appears to have been established in 1921.
The administration of the school remained vested in elected deans until 1891. In that year the regents amended their bylaws, giving themselves exclusive power to appoint deans. The effect of this decision on the Medical School was to strengthen the dean's position. Between 1850 and 1891 seven men served thirteen terms of office as dean, the average term in office lasting slightly more than three years. The regents' first appointed Dean of the Medical School, Victor C. Vaughan, held the position for thirty years.
Vaughan's retirement, in 1921, saw the Medical School at a highwater mark. Vaughan himself had been a distinguished researcher, author, and educator, as well as a past president of the American Medical Association. He had first come to Michigan in 1874 as a student, and joined the faculty of the Medical School in 1879. He had attracted to Michigan a distinguished faculty, given the school a reputation for educational innovation, and left it one of the nation's pre-eminent medical colleges.
While Michigan remained a leader in medical education after Vaughan's retirement, the faculty was divided by a bitter factional dispute centering around Vaughan's successor as dean, Hugh Cabot. Cabot, a Harvard educated surgeon who had served at Massachusetts General Hospital from 1902 to 1919, proved unable to deal with the situation. Dissension reached the point at which several key faculty members believed the school's continuing success depended upon Cabot's removal as dean. In February 1930 the regents "...in the interests of greater harmony in the Medical School," removed Cabot from his position as dean and authorized the president of the university to appoint a committee of five to direct the affairs of the school.
The Executive Committee, consisted of Frederick G. Novy, chair, James D. Bruce, Harley A. Jaynes, Udo J. Wile, and Arthur C. Curtis. It governed the Medical School until 1933, when one of its number, Frederick Novy, was appointed dean. Novy, a contemporary of Vaughan's, was close to retirement and it seems clear that his appointment was a final honor bestowed upon a senior and distinguished faculty member rather than a permanent selection. Despite the selection of Novy as dean, the Executive Committee continued to play an important role in the administration of the school.
In 1935, a permanent replacement for Cabot was appointed. Perhaps reacting to both the failure of the outsider Cabot and the success of the University of Michigan schooled Vaughan, an internal candidate was chosen as dean. Albert C. Furstenberg had received virtually all of his medical experience at Michigan. The university had awarded him his medical degree in 1915, and he subsequently joined the Medical School's faculty. Furstenberg's appointment did little to rein in the virtually independent faculty. The Executive Committee continued to meet regularly, and the various departments, which had always acted with independence, now possessed virtual sovereignty. Throughout his tenure as dean, Furstenberg exercised his authority with needed diplomacy.
After the conclusion of the Second World War the Medical School, like the rest of the university, experienced rapidly increasing demands for service. Most important were repeated requests by the state legislature that the school expand to increase the number of doctors available in the state. Coupled with this request were other requests that the number of out-of-state students be reduced or eliminated entirely. From a 1940 base of 120 members per class, the numbers of students in each class slowly increased to 165 in 1951. In 1952, the opening of new physical facilities allowed class size to increase to 204. This number slowly increased for the next thirty years, reaching approximately 235. The school also voluntarily imposed a drastic limit on the number of out-of-state students it accepted.
To meet the increasing demands for education, and to staff a vastly increased research program, faculty size grew dramatically. In 1940, the Medical School had approximately 140 faculty members. In 1971, there were 578 faculty members. Physical facilities also grew. Eight major construction projects were undertaken between 1947 and 1955. Between 1955 and 1970 another fourteen projects were undertaken, including the Kresge Research addition (1964), Medical Science II (1969), Towsley Center (1970) and C.S. Mott Children's Hospital (1970). Throughout the 1970s planning was undertaken for the construction of a new University Hospital to replace the often renovated structure constructed in 1925. The Replacement Hospital Project dominated thinking throughout the decade.
Expanded physical facilities proved inadequate to deal with the complex education needs of the Medical School. To better meet these needs, the school entered into agreements with several affiliated or "core" hospitals. St. Joseph Mercy Hospital, Veterans Administration Hospital (Ann Arbor), Wayne County General Hospital, and Henry Ford Hospital (Detroit), all formally agreed to offer clinical educational resources to medical students from the University of Michigan.
Governing the vastly expanded Medical School became an increasingly complex problem. In 1940, administration consisted of the dean, the secretary of the faculty, the three member Executive Committee, and a registrar or recorder. In 1947, the first associate dean, Maurice H. Seevers, was appointed. Throughout the remainder of Dean Furstenberg's term of office he was aided by either an associate or assistant dean.
In 1959, Furstenberg was succeeded as dean by William N. Hubbard, Jr. Hubbard had received his medical training in New York City, and had continued to reside there, serving as an associate dean of the New York University College of Medicine, until his appointment as dean in Ann Arbor. He quickly expanded the administrative structure of his predecessor. In 1960-1961, he appointed a new assistant dean, and added three new assistants to the dean, one of them being J. A. Diana who was responsible for business operations. In 1961-1962, he revived the title associate dean, unused since 1951, and added that position to the new positions now in place. Among Hubbard's appointments to these many positions were Alexander Barry (1963-1964), Fred Hodges (1965-1966), Robert A. Green (1967-1968), and George R. DeMuth (1968-1969).
In 1969, a sweeping reform occurred in the administration of the entire hospital hill complex. The University Hospital Study and Advisory Committee, chaired by Fedele F. Fauri (commonly referred to as the Fauri Committee), and appointed by University President Robben Fleming, recommended combining the administration of the hospital and the medical school under a single person, the Director of the University of Michigan Medical Center. This recommendation, and several others, were carried out by the regents on February 21, 1969. The position was given to Hubbard, who also continued to serve as dean of the Medical School.
In 1970, Hubbard was replaced as dean by John A. Gronvall. Gronvall also became director of the Medical Center. Gronvall, like Hubbard, continued to modify the administrative structure of the Medical School. In 1972-1973, he appointed Thomas J. Herrmann as associate dean, and added two new assistant deans to the school, one of them Charles L. Votaw. In subsequent years, Gronvall recognized the importance of the various affiliated hospitals by appointing separate assistant deans to oversee educational activities in each of them. While overseeing the modification of the administrative structure of the Medical School itself, Gronvall also took part in the dismantling of much of the Fauri Committee's work. Dissatisfaction with the way the administrative structures proposed by the committee actually worked led, in December 1974, to a reorganization of the entire administrative structure. The Medical Center as an administrative entity was abolished, and Dean Gronvall was no longer required to exercise direct administrative oversight of hospital operations.
In 1982, Dean Gronvall resigned from his position as dean. Peter A. Ward served as interim dean from 1982 to 1985. Seizing in part on the fact that the Medical School was administered by an interim dean, university president Harold Shapiro recommended to the regents in 1983 the creation of a new office of vice provost for medical affairs. The dean of the Medical School and the executive director of the University Hospital would report to the new vice provost who in turn would report to the vice president for academic affairs and provost. This arrangement was designed to provide a single node of responsibility for the Medical Center, while maintaining the Medical School within the overall academic structure of the university. On April 1, 1984, George D. Zuidema was appointed as vice provost for medical affairs.
In 1985, Joseph E. Johnson was named as dean of the Medical School. Johnson remained until 1990, after which Giles Bole served first as acting dean, then as dean, beginning in 1991. In 1994, Zuidema retired as vice provost for medical affairs. At that time the position was reevaluated and reconfigured as vice provost for health affairs. On July 1, 1994, Rhetaugh Dumas was appointed to the re-designated vice provost position.
In 1996 Giles Bole resigned as dean and was succeeded by Lorris Betz as interim dean. In 1998 Allen S. Lichter succeeded Betz as interim dean before being appointed dean. A new position was created in 1997, Executive Vice President for Medical Affairs. Gilbert Omenn was named to this new position in September 1997.
Medical School Deans (Elected)
1850-1851 Abram Sager
1851-1853 Samuel Denton
1853-1857 Silas H. Douglass
1857-1858 Samuel Denton
1858-1859 Moses Gunn
1859-1861 Abram Sager
1861-1863 Corydon L. Ford
1863-1868 Silas H. Douglass
1868-1875 Abram Sager
1875-1879 Alonzo B. Palmer
1879-1880 Corydon L. Ford
1880-1887 Alonzo B. Palmer
1887-1891 Corydon L. Ford
Medical School Deans (Appointed)
1933-1935 Frederick G. Novy
1935-1959 Albert C. Furstenberg
1959-1970 William N. Hubbard, Jr.
1970-1982 John A. Gronvall
1982-1985 Peter A. Ward (interim)
1985-1990 Joseph E. Johnson III
1990 Giles G. Bole (acting)
1991-1996 Giles G. Bole
1996-1998 A. Lorris Betz (interim)
1998 Allen S. Lichter (interim)
1998-2006 Allen S. Lichter
2007 James O. Wolliscroft
The records of the Medical School span over 125 years, beginning in 1850 and continuing through 2002. They include 323 linear feet of material, ten oversized volumes and six oversized folders of miscellaneous documents. The records include dean's correspondence and subject files, executive committee minutes, faculty minutes, annual reports of departments, school accreditation and review files, a variety of special reports and studies, and extensive files on the Replacement Hospital Project (Taubman Center). The record group also contains photo prints depicting faculty, students and facilities, including a remarkable series of photographs taken by J. Jefferson Gibson ca. 1893.
The Medical School records have been organized into five subgroups: Dean's Records, Subordinate Administrative Officers, Faculty Records, Audio-Visual Materials, and Miscellaneous records. Within each subgroup there are a number of series and these series may be further subdivided to reflect the date span of the records received in each accession.
The Medical School records have been received in several accessions and the physical arrangement of the records (the number order of the boxes) reflects the various installments in which they were received. The accessions sometimes reflected the tenure of a particular dean or other administrator, but frequently appear to have been somewhat arbitrary transfers of files. Records from individual subgroups, series and subseries often continue across multiple accessions--sometimes with consecutive date ranges, but often with overlapping date spans.
In this finding aid the records are described in their intellectual order -- like subgroups and series are brought together irrespective of the particular accession in which they were received. As a result, in the detailed contents listing the box number order will not always be consecutive.
The Medical School Records were received in a number of accessions. The list below provides a box number order listing at the subgroup and series level.
Summary Box Listing
Dean's Records subgroup, 1915-1981 -- boxes 1-83
Committees and Councils, 1930-1981 -- boxes 1-31
Correspondence, 1915-1959 -- boxes 32-73
Departmental Annual and Special Reports, 1959-1979 -- boxes 73-77
Administrative Files, 1950-1979 -- boxes 77-83
Subordinate Administrative Officers subgroup, 1929-1982 -- boxes 83-126
Alexander Barry, 1961-1969 -- boxes 83-86
George R. DeMuth, 1964-1977 -- boxes 86-90
Robert A. Green, 1961-1977 -- boxes 90-96
Thomas J. Herrmann, 1960-1977 -- boxes 96-104
Fred J. Hodges, 1960-1972 -- box 104
Walter G. Rice, 1961-1975 -- boxes 105-112
James A. Taren, 1943-1982 -- boxes 112-114
Charles A. Votaw, 1929-1977 -- boxes 115-127
Faculty Records subgroup, 1850-1976 -- boxes 127-134)
Miscellaneous Records
Primarily of the 19th and Early 20th Century, 1850-1971 -- box 135
Miscellaneous reports -- box 161
School flag, Vaughan Memorial -- unbound Bimu/C46
Audio-Visual Materials subgroup
Photographs -- boxes 136, 214, and oversize folders
Films -- box 136
Dean's Records subgroup (Additional), 1930-1982 -- boxes 144-161
Committees and Councils, 1930-1982 -- boxes 144-156
Administrative Files, 1967-1982 -- boxes 157-160
Miscellaneous Reports, 1971, 1980-1982 -- box 161
Dean's Records subgroup (Additional), 1956-1984 -- boxes 162-178
Departmental Files, 1956-1984 -- boxes 162-167
Administrative Files, 1959-1984 -- boxes 167-177
Dean's Records subgroup (Additional), 1960-1988 -- boxes 179-182
Administrative Files, 1960-1988 -- boxes 179-182
Committees and Councils, 1979-1983 -- box 182
Subordinate Administrative Officers subgroup (Additional, 1961-1991 -- boxes 182-199, 214-215
David Bachrach, 1977-1984 -- boxes 182-186
Thomas Herrmann, 1961-1981 -- boxes 197-191
Donald Lentz, 1969-1978 -- boxes 195-199
John Niederhuber, 1983-1985 -- box 191
Robert Reed, 1972-1984 -- boxes 192-195, 214-215
Dean's Records subgroup (Additional), 1971, 1975-1984 -- boxes 200-209
Committees and Councils (Executive Committee), 1979-1983 -- boxes 200-209
Reports, 1971, 1975-1984 -- box 209
Dean's Records subgroup (Additional), 1960-1990 -- boxes 216-238
Departmental Files, 1977-1990 -- boxes 216-222
Administrative Files, 1960-1990 -- boxes 223-238
Dean's Records subgroup (Additional), 1960-1988 -- boxes 239-252
Committees and Councils, 1977-1989 -- boxes 239-252
Subordinate Administrative Officers subgroup (Additional), 1986-1998 -- boxes 253-259
Giles G. Bole, 1986-1991 -- boxes 253-257
John E. Billi, 1990-1998 -- boxes 258-259
Dean's Records subgroup (Additional), 1968-1998 -- boxes 260-317
Committees and Councils, 1987-1996 -- boxes 260-274
Departmental Files, 1978, 1981-1996 -- boxes 275-284
Administrative Files, 1983-1998 -- boxes 285-310
Miscellaneous Files, 1968-1975, 1980-1996 -- boxes 311-314
Correspondence, 1990-1997 -- boxes 315-317
Subordinate Administrative Officers subgroup (Additional), 1990-2002 -- boxes 318-323
John E. Billi, 1990-1998 -- boxes 318-323
Dean's Records subgroup (Additional
Alan C. Lichter files, 1998=2006 -- online
Subjects:
Academic freedom.; Affirmative action programs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; African Americans--Michigan.; American Medical Association.; Animal welfare.; Association of American Medical Colleges.; Cabot, Hugh, 1872-1945.; Detroit College of Medicine and Surgery.; Flexner, Abraham, 1866-1959.; Furstenberg, Albert Carl, 1890-1969.; Gronvall, John Arnold, 1931-; Henry Ford Hospital.; Hospitals--Michigan.; Hubbard, William Neill, 1919-; Medicine--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Michigan Association for Regional Medical Programs.; Michigan Coordinating Council for Public Higher Education. Committee to Consider the Location and Sponsorship of the Expansion of Medical Education.; St. Joseph Mercy Hospital (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan--Commencements.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Anatomy.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Anesthesiology.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Biological Chemistry.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Dermatology.; University of Michigan--Dept. of Neurology.; University of Michigan--Examinations.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan--Students.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.; University of Michigan. Replacement Hospital Project.; University of Michigan. University Union Relations Advisory Committee.; Veterans Administration Hospital (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Wayne County General Hospital.; Minority college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; World War, 1914-1918--Education and the war.; World War, 1914-1918--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; World War, 1939-1945--Education and the war.; World War, 1939-1945--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.; Hospitals--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Laboratories.; Medicine--1890-1899.; Gibson, J. Jefferson.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Dean's Records 1915-1996
  The largest subgroup in the Medical School record group is the Dean's Records, dating from 1915 to 1996. The Dean's Records have been divided into six series: Committee and Council Records, Executive Committee, Correspondence Files, Departmental Files, Administrative Records, and Miscellaneous Files. Filing practices varied over the years with the result that there may be gaps in some series. The Correspondence series, for example, has no material for the years 1960-1989. Presumably, items that had been filed as correspondence were filed under another category for those years.
  - Committee and Council Series 1930-1996
    The Committee and Council Records Series (1930-1996) consists of various committees and councils that reported to the dean, were appointed by the dean, or on which the dean served or held an interest. The subseries is further subdivided by time spans reflecting materials received in various accessions. Records of a particular committee may extend over several of the accessions. Files of individual committees may include minutes correspondence and other material.